so I had several suit does about energy
and effort have them kind of general
discussion about that what I mean but it
when it but it says that mmm so first
thing I'll read is uh from Sangeeta
nakiya Bojan Nestle Newton the third suta
Bojan Nestle Newton the third suta
that's on the Enlightenment factors says
starts off because those bhikkhus who
are accomplished in virtue accomplished
in composure accomplished in wisdom
accomplished in the duration
accomplished in knowledge and written
the liberation even the sight of those
because is helpful I stay even listening
to them even approaching them even
attending on them even recollecting them
even going forth after them is helpful I
say for what reason because when one has
heard the demo from such a bhikkhu when
dwells withdrawn by to cut one of two
kinds of by way of two kinds of
withdrawal withdrawal of the body and
withdrawal of the mind dwelling thus
withdrawn one recollected Ummah and
thinks it over on that occasion
enlightenment factor of mindfulness is
aroused by the bhikkhu and that occasion
that we could develop the Enlightenment
factor of mindfulness and that occasion
the alignment factor of my class comes
to fulfillment by development in that
beaker dwelling thus mindfully he
discriminates at demo with wisdom
examines it makes an investigation of it
and whenever he does that he's mindfully
developing the discrimination of states
or investigation factor while he
discriminates that Demma with wisdom and
examines it his energy is aroused
without slackening whenever a big whose
energy is a rather thought slackening as
he investigates the devil with wisdom
examines it on that occasion the
Enlightenment factor of energy is
aroused by the big GU and after that it
says when his energy has aroused there
arises in him spirit at Pt translated
rapture usually
whenever bhikkhus rapture arrives bhiku
energy whose energies aroused on that
occasion the end alignment factor of
rapture is aroused and then I'll stop
after this one fruit did for one whose
mind is uplifted by a rapture the body
becomes tranquil and the mind becomes
tranquil whenever bhikkhus the body
becomes Trank when the mind becomes
tranquil and a big lose minds uplifted
by rapture on that occasion
enlightenment factor of tranquillity is
aroused by the big food so the sound of
air like you know at first glance again
think of energy is always as kind of a
like kind of over energized that seems
to me the usual kind of assumption but
it's here saying that it's clearly
within the framework of well it's also
what's the sake of that apply energy
well it's for having a certain kind of
tranquillity but then people over think
overdue tranquility - so um as far as
that goes
what what is that what exactly is that
kind of energy that allows for one to be
tranquil and not to be like that kind of
assumption that we have of just like too
much well it's not it's not an
inspiration to do something which is
usually requires too much requires you
to be externally inspired so to speak
find external reasons they were
motivated to do things it's more like
the recognition from the well the
recognition of the right view first of
all then because see the work did you
need to do in terms of freeing yourself
from suffering is nowhere else except
within your presently enduring situation
whatever it is so it's not in the future
not in the past
it's right here so if you're not free
from suffering right here right now is
because right here right now you are
still entertaining craving or the view
of craving so once you actually discern
that that work is not just that it's not
elsewhere you also discerned that it's very doable
you also discerned that it's very doable
and it's the recognition of that
durability of the things you still need
to do the ones that still hasn't fulfill
the goal of our own trip naturally give
the energy to do it because you know
that if there is something that you need
to do that's really like to require so
much preparation so far away in the
future it's hard to get motivated to do
it but when you recognize that doing
this is literally only on you and up to
you and within you doesn't require
anything anyone outside same with
tranquility as well you're not
practicing tranquility in order to be
not be bothered by this person by that
person it's just the natural calmness
because you realize it's entirely up to
you and then of course you would you
would want to develop it because it's
obviously very agreeable
so it sounded it sounds to me also like
it's it's a it's like something that uh
it is not like it has to be almost like
a steady kind of thing that God read the
other suit that I was gonna mention
that's the one that's quite well-known
this is good during a book of sixes
number 55
because Sona well the venerable Sona was
a Lawrence occlusion the following
course of thought arose in his mind I am
one of the Blessed ones most energetic
disciples yet my mind has not been
liberated from taints by non-singing
now there is wealth and my family and is
possible for me to enjoy my wealth and
do meritorious deeds let me then get up
the training in return to lower life so
I can do enjoy my wealth and do
meritorious deeds but of having known
this course of thought and sona's mind
went and appeared to him and asked him
if he was thinking that Sona says yes
Ponte and then but it asks tell me Sona
in the past when you lived at home
weren't you skilled at the loot
yes Bunty what do you think Sona when
its strings were too tight was your loot
well tuned and easy to play no Monday
when its strings were too loose was your
Luke too well tuned and easy to play no
Monday at Sona when its strings are
neither too tight nor too loose but
adjust into a balanced pitch as your
lute well tuned either play yes Monday
so - Sona if energy is aroused -
forcefully this leads to restlessness if
energy is to lacks this leads to
laziness therefore Sona resolve on a balance
therefore Sona resolve on a balance
vengi achieve evenness of spiritual
faculties and take pick up your sign
there pick up the sign of that you might
translate it so if you if you get the
energy to do the work if you lose the
context if you lose perspective on a
counter that you will become restless
if you don't you want so he's so keen to
approve the craving that he gave into
craving for uprooting it so then that
the energy to do it
by losing the device context in regard
to it he turned it into crane mmm so it
became restlessness or saying the energy
to become the intention to become if you
lose the context already becomes just
lazy careless drowsy sleepy whatever
else but if you keep the context then is
just to comment so that's what means
they're getting maintaining the balance
means maintaining the context as to the
like what the purpose of energy is what
the purpose of tranquility is instead we
were to do that it's a matter of
maintaining mindfulness in regard to it
that's why I can't eat too much of
mindfulness so then the sense it sounds
as though like while you're doing
whatever efforts you're doing it's
almost like I'm good to like really cut
okay well I'm thinking I'm going this
route though why don't I check on the
perspective of things now yeah like it's
not it's not up to you to decide or I
need energy now I mean you can discern
that sure if that's what the situation
dictates but you can go go let me just
develop some energy so you want to
recognize first of course the mindful
context doesn't what is the purpose of
all of this it's freedom from craving
always you never never never steers away
from the purpose so do you feel like
clear about the direction of freedom
from craving if you clear enough in a
way then okay so keep the keep the
context in your mind in a sense of the
purposes to be free from craving so I
need to understand craving so how can I
make the effort to understand the
craving without needing to create
for the left foot without needing to
wine myself up in order I'll do it now
so how can I get the energy without
allowing that energy to make me Restless
by again not losing the right order of
mindfulness not losing the side of
mindfulness doesn't matter like you find
out that it's more important to not act
out of craving even if you haven't
understood craving yet it's when you
forget that that's more important you
then choose to make more important let
me just act out of this craving and then
I'll figure it out and then I'll never
crave again and then you end up just
just revolving in a vicious circle
because you yourself maintain the
craving in order to understand the way
out of craving but the way out of
craving is by cessation of craving not
better standing it in your own on your
own terms
then so if you if you believe then see
what I can't place on there you don't
want to if you feel muddled about the
intention behind that you need to know
the intention behind yeah so I want to
contemplate this why is it because I
want to get rid of the unpleasantness of
craving means you're acting all craving
oh no I don't wanna feel anything
unpleasant I just want to invest so my
foot into like you know staring a few
things up you know to create a work
because the mind was a bit dull yeah
that's fine but if your mind is not
doubt then it's just too tight so then
you actually want to be no I will not
lose perspective see not acting out of
craving does not automatically mean I'll
just go and sleep and be lazy and drawly
he doesn't it just means you don't lose
the mindfulness you don't sacrifice the
priority of mindful context on account
of what you want to do even if it's to
understand craving so if you're not sure
why you're trying to understand the
craving as in is this rooted in trying
to get rid of the suffering
what is it maybe root means you're
doubtful means you should calm yourself
first and you count yourself first by
maintaining absence of craving is more
important than acting out of craving
even for the sake of getting rid of the
craving and you are responsible for
absence of craving or for presence of
craving cuz craving need action to be
maintained you need to act out of it so
if you're not acting out of it you does
okay that's all I need to do for now now
when there is no pressure of craning
then the mind can maybe think if you
want to still think about this think
about the often you realize the reason
you want to understand craving was just
to get rid of the pain
they was currently felt and that's
already routine crane
so don't lose the context for example on
the unpleasantness of restlessness then
it will become the energy for the
internment of kind of being done yeah
exactly yeah then it'll become college I don't
yeah then it'll become college I don't
need to have anything happening all the
time we're all the time figuring things
up why is that so why do i by default
habitually try to get rid of this
unpleasantness is because you still
prioritize your views that I must be
doing this I must be doing that I must
begin a little bit but even then is
rooted in simply wanted to be free from
suffering by being free from craving so
why we go around creating craving that
makes you suffer in order to be free
from it initially yeah everybody has to
do that but the point needs to come when
you recognize it okay now if the mind is
free from craving all I need to do is
stay mindful with that and then make
sure that it doesn't turn into craving
you protect it you don't need to
constantly sort of product and product
and product because again it will become
too tight
so what do you think in terms of like
things that people can pick up all you
know it says like picking up the signs
of when the mind is too much like this
or too much like that because obviously
you know inevitably people are going to
make the mistakes and go too far one way
or the other and so it seems that the
Buddhist thing is important to like
recognize when this is in fact happening
discerning when that is happening yeah
well you discern what that's happening
will you dissent the context of your
action of what you're about to do will
be your engaging you don't like
preemptively discerning oh look look
look it's here because it's not
necessary problem in itself the problem
is as I said when on account of your
energy slash restlessness you try to get
rid of the pain through acting out of
pain hmm so you maintain the craving and
regard to it which is going to make them
more Restless because you know it
requires it for its own for their very
action so you discern what president is this is
so you discern what president is this is
my situation am i trying to get rid of
him am i trying to descend gravy now
because I just want to get rid of the
discomfort of of restlessness so am I
trying to understand them because it's
really unpleasant when my mind is like
not thinking about anything no
engagement with the it frightens me
discerning that so let is step forward
to know that out of it right you can't
like make a checklist of signs to pick
up exactly that's what signs are that's
what they look at this generic name
signs and tokens we it's just
characteristics of what's there so what
is the main context what is the
characteristic of the main context here
is fundamentally I'm just acting out of
suffering I'm trying to get rid of this
unpleasant stage of whatever darkness no
I'm thinking and what not just mind is a
bit slow I don't like it that deal feel
guilty feel bad if we must do this you
must do that why because this is
unpleasant so you end up acting out of
the same principle that people act
further back which is a principle that
keeps you bond to the action so that's
when you reckon is no hold on I'm not
acting I'm not engaging in anything I've
also my body my speed my mind so the
darkness of the mind is not my darkness
it doesn't need to be my problem it's
just a phenomenon there's current state
of mind that's when satipatthana so
they've done rightly the mindfulness of
the on the level of the mind would be he
knows his mind is elated mind elated
mind is innate in mind he knows he's
depressed mind as depressed mind he
knows his dog - don't mind quick - quick
my sharp sharp slow slow doesn't matter
he's just a state of mind but it's you
who tries to get rid of it on account of
discomfort you might cause you so stop
acting from out of the way you feel
it's the same principle that kind of
common to energy turning into
restlessness or calmness turning into
sloth and torpor losing the context in
regard to how it makes you feel remember
me said that I realized that I had been
just fighting off dullness the whole
time of this talk and as I was having
trouble formulating more questions that
was like why this afternoon yeah
sometimes as low as sometimes you fasted
the matter what matters is losing the
context on account wit and you lose the
context when you choose to engage off
let's get the drill is down and so I'll
give in to the dollars but I must get
rid of the the the restlessness or I'll
give in to restlessness
either way you engage with it how about
I can stay mindfully you got to how I
feel about the restlessness or while I'm
Restless how I feel while I'm slow how I
feel while I'm doubtful I feel while
there is sensual inclinations because I
think that's that's what's common to all
the hindrances by the way is acting on
account of paint sensuality is
unpleasant you act towards it to get rid
of it you will it's like a sting it's
unpleasant so you won't act out black
shot to get rid of it to replace it to
tell you it again if if it were not felt
unpleasantly you wouldn't be anything
out of it
and same for the other hindrance is
doubt as well trying to figure things
out phases and not because they need
figuring out or because you like clarity
or not enough information about it
simple because doubtful state is very
unpleasant so you're just trying to get
rid of how you feel on one level by
acting on a completely different level
or figuring this out they will then make
me feel good even if it does so you're
still acted out of the way you felt and
as such you still remain fully pressured
subjected contacted by the feeling which
means you always will be for as long as
you keep maintaining
affection so you want to learn how to
act without needing to act out of a
feeling and you learn how to act without
needing general feeling but I couldn't
what's already there that doesn't
require you or your action now mind is
already there sharp mind is already
there at times Pleasant feeling is
already there unpleasant feelings over
there look body is already there you're
holding the tablet scratching your arm
whatever you're not thinking you don't
need to attend to every second it's
already happening and you don't need to
stop it in order to recognize it you
just need to realize it is a whole
domain of things already happening they
do not require your volition your
interference your greed your aversion
your delusion your views your
assumptions completely redundant but
it's learning to see that domain has
actually more fundamental than the
domain of your volition your choices you
will wishes your desires your assumption
and so on
you said to check how you feel in
regards to a thing so it's not so than
saying like anyway it's almost obvious
that yeah it's gonna be painful but like
how do I feel about the pain is more
important yeah yeah but I asked you the
other day oh so what you got a moment my
current mood is a bit unpleasant how did
you feel about that mood do you feel
like all these movies are present and I
must understand it means that's what
your mood is really it's how you feel in
regard to your mood is where your mood
is thank you sir maybe your arms are
bothered by the pain that I may say I
feel okay about it
fine yes okay so I did it's unpleasant
but doesn't need to be anything more
than that unless you lose the sight of
it and then automatically start leaning
towards trying to get rid of it
so then it's as far as the these
Energy's going to be talking about
energy and energy and stuff it's
obviously there's nothing mystical about
it yeah of course but in terms like the
you know and the better talking about
energy then what are we exactly
referring to so I'll read that the for
right strivings okay exactly that's what
willingness readiness for effort
that's what energy is it's almost like
not always after them preparedness yes
yeah you're ready I can I don't need to
spend three hours thinking I need to do
this work no one is that I do it and no
work needs to be done up still energetic
without needing to extant and kind of
engage with things because I'm so full
of energy no you have energy means you
are ready to act properly if lost you
are ready to not entertain it if normos
you're ready to protect it you so that's
why energy wisely with the right context
it's effortless it's all you doing okay
so how is his tireless energy that's
what all this energy is exactly doesn't
tell you you don't need to be tiring
yourself out of that energy it's just
endless energy because it's it's an
endless resonance
and that is a state of mind independent
of your action it depends on your
understanding and the context the
clarity of the context
so there's a for great striving pizzetta
here because the good generates desire
for the non arising of under isn't evil
unwholesome states makes an effort
arouses energy causes mind and strives
he generates for the abandoning of
arisen evil and wholesome states he
makes an effort so on he generates for
the arising of utter is in wholesome
states he makes an effort arouses energy
apply his mind he generates for the
desire for the maintenance of arisen
wholesome states for their non decay
increase expansion and fulfilment by
development these are the four rights
Driving's so you mentioned like and
effortless energy preparedness kind of
thing so so I just see it's so it's just
say
they lost the question it's mine still
de yeah no that's alright the its if
done rightly but as arousing a little
energy against the backdrop of the right
context it's same like with the arising
of or maintenance of mindfulness it's
it's effortless and it's also not
unpleasant if awry like if you need to arise the
if awry like if you need to arise the
arouse the energy and it feels like a
chore and it's unpleasant means there is
the element of of restlessness that
bothers you means you're acting out of
craving like what why you ask yourself
why do you need to arise and enjoy them
like regain the context for energy not
sense of duty or because somebody said
oh because I must be energetic then it's
you can't sustain that why why do each
other's energy and when he says why to
dispel the unwholesome oh so I did an
awesome state that need a spelling No
so what am i arising energy for maybe
I'm worried energetic I just don't see
it cuz I turn it interested and it's by
default as in I am ready to deal with
things when they come
that doesn't mean you keep going
inviting them to come quite the opposite
you learn to recognize when they are not
there then okay now it's a different
energy so the energy must deal with this cuz
so the energy must deal with this cuz
nothing to do with it I just must
protect this and you protect it by not
trying to deal with it hmm so even in
sense of like sometimes you know it
seems I cannot assume like you know here
a little bit dull a little bit tired the
obvious thing at surface is just kind of
route yourself but it's not always
necessarily the right thing to be doing
knows you're like passing out or
something exactly so I feel drowsy and
tired why
I'm not sure why I just feel that way
okay so is it a problem am I giving it
to last and I can't do this No am i
giving in to anger your will acontece no
am i performing actions of distracting
nature an account of it no okay that's
what I need to do not give in to these
things I don't need to get rid of this
because I didn't I've seen it's rising
and then you realize maybe because you
didn't sleep well last night maybe cuz
your time because you didn't eat enough
maybe because you're sick who knows what
would the reason is doesn't matter what
matters is why do you act out of it I
must always gives you the fatigue and
tiredness it's impossible because the
body gets fatigued and tired you just
don't want to act out of losing the
context you and I act out of habit out
of a duty out of it whatever it's
usually a habit because in the beginning
of you don't really can't see the the
threshold of the entrances so then
everything didn't nothing is a problem
my problem is that you don't see a
problem is it's not there you make up
you make it into a problem so inevitably
after work work your way through that
but the point has to come when you
recognize it yeah okay I'm down I'm
tired I can't think that's on the
problem the problem is when I choose to
act towards greed to a deal will
aversion hatred towards distraction
carelessness out of this feeling and
that's a clear choice so you just don't
act then and you don't need to do
anything with it
you've mentioned before and by the way
same if look I must figure this out why
is it because I want to get it into it
so I'm acting out of it just on the
level of the mind and you mentioned like
if there's doubt or ambiguity it is kind
of probably on that side of things
what do you mean like you want to be
reading what I can't there's something I
want to do something it's like almost
like you're not you're finding different
reasons so you're not really finding the
right oh yeah sure sure
you're not even clear as to why you just
keep looking for something to do just
look almost like you using your minds
parent give justice well it's like
acting out of docks yeah you see like
you can as I said many times before you
can only doubt the content of your
experience of your thought of the idea
whatever your doubtful about but you
can't doubt did you experience in nature
doubt that you are under the pressure of
doubt you cannot doubt that but losing
the sight that that's what's first
that's where the problem is you then
give in to try to clarify the content
deal with the content 3 explain the
content revisit the content 3 read the
content hash out the content again
because it doesn't make me feel right
doesn't make you feel right because dog
is not pleasant that's it you don't want
to feel not pleasant
it sounds really a question of well you
should if you're being affected by the
doubt that's the first question it is
and that's that's the work that you've
been mentioning like the work sounds
like it's not what you assume the work
has to be at any exam exam yeah you may
well be like looking past where the work
already is yeah yeah more often than not
I think that's the case cuz you act out
of this all phases of um no my work is
the telling where what's presently
enduring no but what my sense of duty
dictates and even is that okay so sense
of duty how did i acquire that sense of
duty and you knew as you fight it before
you were aware of any context when you
just adopted it is is a must on account
of faith on a kind of external
instruction which is fine but if you
remember bound to it you remain bound to
syllabus Varma's acting out of the sense
of duty without actually discernment of
what's presently there and what
presently is addressing which means you
won't be seeing the mind free from lust
as mine free from lust you won't be
seeing mine effective lust is mine
effective with us and we dangle in
distraction cuz you're just taking out sense of duty
cuz you're just taking out sense of duty
always regardless of what the state of
mind is and by doing so you end up
appropriating your state of mind
do you have anything you wanted to bring
hmm sometimes I've seen the translation for
sometimes I've seen the translation for
energy as zeal and it made me think of
the first day you get bread you know
seeing a teacher or accomplished because
instead of like having this arousal of
energy more of a zeal and a sense of
confidence like recognizing that's like
in the other services
yeah man interesting he's on welfare
goes and with visits wise men and then
the lens they understand what they say
then he measures the task just like a
prerequisite for the zeal oh this is
what needs to be done you can't be
zealous about the task we have no idea
at all just do everything in nothing
I'll just pray on meditative watch my
nostril and then the work will be done
for me no exactly and exactly what needs
to be done to free yourself from
suffering so that's it it's doable by
knowing what needs to be done you make
it doable and then the energy will arise
from it yeah okay
could that also be like a sense of
urgency like seeing that well say yeah
yeah I think center agents will be more
of like up you know a prod they would
result in energy but yeah yeah it's
connected to that like oh no just oh
there's this one that needs to be done
but I can afford to not do it know you
recognize oh it needs to be done and now
I know what it is and it's like it's a
must it's an imperative you will have to
do it but because now you're recognized
for what it is it doesn't feel like this
is a big use sort of non defined short
it oppresses you but you can't really
put your finger on it you know exactly
what suffering is but freedom from
suffering is you know exactly what
suffering is what freedom from suffering
is and you know exactly what you do to
develop it
so that yeah that's why the right view
needs to come first otherwise there is
no right effort we don't like you
and then people in the effort if it's
not in line with right view and the
effort is wrong and it could be just
because of that sort of like oh I feel
unpleasant feelings but if you know if
you have that understanding of that like
you understand the feeling or you
understand that you're not allowing
craving to basically take you here and
there you're applying the effort rightly
well you're certainly closer to that
yeah yeah but not just I must I must act
out of this to get rid of this to
recognize it you're acting on account of
how you feel
which means craving has to be there you
know you can't directly seek out this is
my craving but you can know based on the
inclination towards the present enduring
feeling am I trying to get rid of this
means I am craving against it I am the
craving against it I am the craving for
it
so that's why you can't just all just be
present just be here just always do the
same thing because it's not mind is not
always in the same state so you can act
for the right reason but not but acting
just because of a feeling that is the
wrong reason exactly that's gonna make
it wrong that's why you're still not
gonna be freeing yourself from craving
you might talk about it's my duty to to
contemplate into walking meditation you
know why because you need something to
do because you're Restless because it's
unpleasant because you wanna get rid of
the pain well because you really want to
maintain the state that's free from
craving that you understood so
that seems like a lot of the work to me
like making working to not have work so
to speak yeah that's why you start doing
it rightly it ceases to be work that's
why you say oh they do practice the
Dharma you know full of joy and delight
because it's effortless it's like again
you've s the work in adjusting your
strings of your lute but once you get it
right it's just effortless music just
flows and then you will you adjust it
when needs to be adjusted not all I'm
just part of you playing he's adjusting
it that's not play select for example
let's say the suta like there's a point
imagine in the cutoff that it would be
here one word mentioned like thing or
the way of stilling were calming ever
know he was distracting thoughts no such
transit yeah sure like that one I think
a lot of people and it's misinterpreted
is like my dream is when this is here
you know that exactly that means either
way you keep acting as a kind of
unpleasantness so much there and that is
on the level of doing which is why it's
unpleasant to do you have to do it I
have to respond to this and that's what
it's always going to be a burden but if
you do it rightly it's not from the
level of do it easily it's on the level
of the service which is effortless
because things you discern a little dim
death you don't need to develop them
create them or bring them back or
something they're less you just need to
stop distracting yourself from them
through your efforts of doing them
that's a big with trying too hard to be
mindful that's why you're not mindful so
you're looking at the wrong place
mindfulness is not on the level of the
toy it's on the level of intention
behind your doing so the level of
present enduring feelings which is a
basis for your doing so the level of the
present enduring mood or the body which
is a basis for your action yet here you
are a mindful a mindful
mindful you're doing it and that's why
you're not mine
so interns in it sounds like it
something like okay you have you are
properly enduring whatever then
wholesome thought is arisen and kind of
these features you've read about them
they will become apparent because if
you're not because now you're providing
the basis for those features to be
discerned because they are and on those
on those levels but you were not seeing
it cuz you want to familiar enough it
senses think it's not like maybe sure
that you're choosing is not the right
term in terms of how people do you think
I'm gonna choose now to respond like
this yeah yeah it's not it's it precedes
your choice it's it's even precedes your
attention in a way that's why I keep
saying like mindfulness is about
discerning the context knowing what's
already there without needing to attend
to it - no that's already there the only
reason you can attend to what you feel
is cuz you are already feeling it means
there's already a recognition of what's
being felt but you choose to ignore that
put it second you choose to compromise
that by allowing no still when I attend
to it now I know it's there but you
already knew what was there see with the
body you don't need to keep attending to
yourself that you're seated now you just
seated and if I were to ask you out of
the blue what's your position I'm seated
now you can choose to attend to it as
well but the only reason is because you
already know that you're seated
so it's discerning that knowledge did
without attending it even if you don't
so you have to resist the need to attend
it and learn to discern what you already
know and not okay but I'll still attend
it no that means you won't know it on
the same level because you chose still
to act out of what you attend as in what
you chose so you still want to make
things to be on your own terms
and that's that kind of compulsive based
some people money to distrain like even
when you know you still choose to give
in to okay now limit anything really
confirm what I already know
in other words oh let me still allow
myself to act out of how I feel
did I already know how I feel but I want
to act out of it anyway
so that's your own dependence on your
own craving that you're fully
responsible for and you you're
maintaining through that type of action
that's like your recent talked about the
mindful I don't know how researchers
mindful forgetting like forgetting
properly means not remembering wrongly
yes exactly and then in terms of liking
of mindfulness brings composure that
composure and that base it's like on the
level of that mind floats not that's
something like you think of now
composure is like more known
no no more attentive or something no
it's just more of an unshakeable context
that's what composure is means say it's
Morton almost like terrible including
more yes exactly
less pitiful not that it's always on
your mind no no no it's just what he
means there and he doesn't get perturbed
by things you do attend to choose to do
within that that's when our hunt who has
mindfulness that's imperturbable
to its fullness still speak Stokes was
the tallest eats whatever cannot be
discerned external the whole look is
gliding in the air cuz he's in our heart
no can telling apart often they couldn't
often other arahants couldn't tell them
apart natosi would understanding is how do you
natosi would understanding is how do you
understand this okay yeah he's mighty
most likely free even the Buddha
couldn't always tell is it yeah he's
free maybe but if they saw as did you
left you know a little bit somewhere
unspecified who knows to what extent
he'll be reborn in those great heavens
and then become another in
become a non-return so it's it's again
it's it's about developing that kind of
context the servant which is what your
mindfulness is to the extent necessary
for like removal of any basis for acting
on greed reversion hatred carelessness
out of distraction boredom all the
unwholesome things that's why they are
also
to board you but would you refer to when
you say carelessness what are you
referring to there I think good luck
carelessness would be so you know you're
a bit muddled you know there might be
some like laziness present and then you
lose context of that so you don't
necessarily go straight into all just do
something lustful or angry but you start
drifting away I'll just go and hang out
for the sake of chitchat not sensual
chitchat but still I'll just going and
you know find some random work because I
need something to do that's already
acting out of carelessness and
distraction almost like not clarifying
your intentions enough yeah because I
don't know it's it'll be fine there's
only exactly yeah
choosing to ignore Oh be up you're right
I can handle it
I can I can I can sort of absorb this
I'll be fine
but see the problem is that did you lose
a context on account of it and that's
why you're not fine even if you yeah
don't go further in your careless
actions nevertheless you gave in to that
extent hmm so that's why you leave it
somebody who is understood the Dhamma
can can distract himself from fulfilling
that understanding by work what was the
other one sleep and talk company it's
just well any company finding many
things to do work that doesn't need to
be but we must be done and then you just
enjoy doing it building things out
repairing things you don't really know
just finding things to do finding
activity finding engagement finding
projects because that's the hard thing
for me like kind of choosing when and
where to actually start investigating my
intentions because there's almost I have
this inclination does attack to check
every thought it's just not possible not
stable of course yeah it's just gonna
wind you up quite unpleasantly because
you keep trying to control the
uncontrollable well let me check it's
them - why why am i checking this then
so let me attend to this let me attend
to this let me attend to this phlegmatic
why are you telling it to discern the
knowledge that this is your attention so
that's a more often than not it's
actually people too keen to get rid of
things even under the pretext of
practicing your Dharma
last week calmness requires learning
like somewhat requires learning requires
understanding what summit is as the
suitors often say the monks were not
skilled they should go and ask those
monks that are skilled in calming the
mind how they come about it and how they
and how the regards and Carters in order
to calm their mind how do I calm my mind
it's all going you just feel one with
the universe
accidentally no you know exactly what
calmness is and then you start
cultivating those signs are not acting
we're not giving in but attend this
attention why but knowing why you want
to do before you do it
chattering how do attend sin Cara's how
did then the determining containers of
for my attention for my action tell me
how to regard them so I'm not fooled by
my attention by my action ok regard them
yeah how to maintain the context in
regard to them how to not lose the sight
of them why why as I said well why would
you be acting out of I need to tender it
thought because the context of it not
attending isn't present is unpleasant
and you obviously lost the sight of it
because now you're trying to control it
through attending and investigating
every second of it but it's all rooted
in the same context that's still there
and that context is the Sun card of all
of your actions it determines the
direction of every single action you do
an account with so how do I then regain
the right perspective of those sin
Cara's hard-wearing garden and then I won't be
hard-wearing garden and then I won't be
fooled by things that I'm attending to
we're needing to or pressure by those
things so it's like it seems like the
most and straightforward to the play one
is like like
discerning how you as we said before how
do I feel about the dislike intention
that I'm doing by doing because I really
like feeling need to do it yeah
clarifying motivation behind your
actions over the beginning of sabotage
because already beginning of unification
seeing the like a day to day life
reasons for doing something is the
Easter you my's unique mind is unified
to that extent throughout all the
actions of doing that thing so you want
to I don't know drink some tea or
something all the little things you do
preparing tea getting together boiling
the water drinking it it's already
unified by an intention to have tea
being drunk but it's usually things that
we are tend to pull us away from what we
already know you already know you want
to have tea you wouldn't know what to
you ordered everything you don't need to
go on so how can you do I need to take
the cup to take the cup put the bag put
the bag no you just do all of that
because it's already unified by the
intention to have the tea extract it
basically from the bank with a hot water
and you already know how to do it so the
context is already there and to that
extent your mind is unified with that
purpose so now find even more general
purpose purpose of not acting out of
cranium make that your context and that becomes
make that your context and that becomes
your unified mind upon never acting out
of craving in regard to whatever tea or
other things doesn't matter if it's
really craving it's not acted out of
could you clarify that context to the
point of actually not mind is unified in
it
so that's that's what it is thought as
opposed to the typical thing to be like
keep asking yourself why you want to tea
while you're doing everything and just
destroy yourself and the fact that there
is something it's already there is you
can Y do about its cause it was already
there you already know what it is and
that's what minutes on that level of
discerning what's already there without
you needing to attend to it hmm your
body postures or the body as a whole and
obviously the more the more effort you
invest in it becomes even like even more
specific things then you can be aware of
peripherally without attending to them
because you know in the beginning
specific things are must focus on us
focus on this but the practice of
somalis opposite direction of practice
of focusing it's not unifying things
through like absorbing in one point but
it's unifying things to find in one
point that unifies everything else
within it
so yeah it is one pointedness it's just
one such a vast point vast container
that whatever occurs within it is seen
against that perspective so that's a
very unified mind so then overall that
in that kind of context are the work to
be done and there are problems and there
are states of craving or craving just
arising mm-hmm not this state that the
craving is um I think their context
would in which craving is and like even
if you kind of have gone into the
craving you know that I start perfectly
you just yet still have that kind of
modus operandi about it sure you include
that in that context because again
doesn't matter how much you were pulled
by the craving in but other since the
choices are the craving you made on
account of that craving it's still
within how you feeling you wouldn't be
making choices of getting rid of the
pain if pain is not felt so not losing
the context of your feeling otherwise
means being probably mindful of your
feelings regardless of the craving of
things none other prey that's where that
sense restraint and virtue needs to be
developed beforehand because when that
has become your when your behavior has
become behavior of non-physical
engagement with sensuality ill-will and
so on that's how you already already
form the context I don't know what I do
but I know what I will not do that's
already a threshold for your start now
within that gloom I know I will not do
that let me invest more I should in
discerning what I'm doing within that
broader non-doing of non-physical
engaging with greed aversion delusion
okay but I am verbal okay so let me not
do that and then it comes to point okay
so I'm mentally and mentally you engage
with it when I said so I will read this
which is a practice Dhamma why I want to
get rid of this paint but not through
like wait a minute so you know together
dependent understand dependence here not
trying to get rid of it by default but
you never see that if your behavior
hasn't been restrained beforehand if
your speech hasn't been
before